In this video, I want to talk about what is
sometimes called wholemeal programming, in
this case on lists.
I already briefly mentioned this concept of
wholemeal programming, as opposed to piecemeal
programming, when we talked about animations
as time-dependent functions.
I mentioned that in CodeWorld, if we define
an animation as a function, then in some sense,
we program the whole animation at once.
So, you don't write a command sequence: first
do this, and then the picture moves there,
and then this happens.
Of course, you use case distinction to distinguish
different cases, but there is one function
as a whole which describes the whole animation
for all time points, instead of having a sequencing.
The same idea of wholemeal programming can
also be applied to lists.
And it is sometimes used in literature as well,
in books.
If you tried to translate this to German,
there's no one-to-one translation, I think,
so piecemeal programming (the opposite of
wholemeal programming) could maybe be translated
as "stückweise" / "allmählich", somewhat
"unsystematisch", whereas for wholemeal programming,
the German translation would maybe be "in
einem Rutsch".
So, to do something at once / in one go, rather
than in many different small steps by looking
at individual list elements by indexing, etc.
In the context of functional programming,
the concept of wholemeal programming is nicely
summarized by these two quotes here.
So, this time, no quote by a medieval king,
but by two former Oxford professors.
Ralf is now at the University of Kaiserslautern
after a few years in Oxford.
And Richard is actually retired by now.
And they both talk here about the same idea:
thinking big.
Thinking about a whole solution at once, a
whole solution space, instead of maybe an
individual solution.
So, the quote by Ralf actually goes on to
talk about, in a setting of graph algorithms,
to think about a graph as a whole, rather
than about individual paths.
So, it is all the same idea: to think about
data structures as a whole thing rather than
talking about individual elements, for example.
Richard here also talks about indexitis.
That's also something that I mentioned before,
when I talked about the index access on lists
being a no-go in Haskell; that it exists,
but you should always try to avoid it, and
write programs by different approaches and
different ideas.
So, that is the same sentiment that Richard
expresses here: to say that indexitis is a
disease which hinders good program design.
And he talks about lawful program construction,
so: having algebraic laws about your programs
is encouraged and helped if you think about
comprehensive operations on your data structures
like lists, instead of piecewise access.
Also dealing with infinite lists is, in some
sense, an outcome of wholemeal programming,
because then you don't want to talk (too much
at least) about individual list elements,
but maybe about lists as a whole, and their
processing.
We could also ask for our functions we have
seen so far, whether or not they are good
examples of wholemeal vs. piecemeal programming.
So, the Quicksort implementation from last
week is not obviously either one.
There is some elementwise processing there.
List comprehensions are often a good example
of wholemeal programming.
So, that also occurred in that example.
If you think about the "isPalindrome" example,
there were two versions in the slides.
There was this version which simply compared
the list with its reverse.
This is a very good example of wholemeal programming,
because we don't touch individual elements,
but simply express a property of the list
as a whole.
Then there was this more recursive definition
which was looking at the first and the last
elements and then did a recursive call.
That's something that maybe doesn't suffer
from indexitis because we never talk explicitly
about indices of data elements in the list.
But even this recursive process is not really
wholemeal programming.
It really talks about the first element and
the last element, makes the list smaller,
etc., instead of the nice reverse-based solution
which simply says: a list is a palindrome
if it is the same as its reverse.
You can't really express it in a more comprehensive
overall way in one go.
That's a very nice example.
In some sense, the version of "isPalindrome"
that I developed in the video just before
this one could also be seen as in the spirit
of wholemeal programming.
Because it also talks about the list as a
whole.
It has a list comprehension, then it says
"and", so everything in this list should be
true.
That is also something where you express something
in one go rather than programming a recursion
over the list structure.
These would be nice examples, and you will
see further examples, of course.
This is another example we have already seen
earlier.
It occurred in the context of discussing why
we do not use for-loops.
And indeed, we don't *have* for-loops because
we have different ways to express something
like a repetition, in this case, of pictures
in a certain scene.
The numbers here are not list indices.
We have [0..5], but this is not list indexing.
It is just a comprehensive way to express
that we have several scenes, and they all
will be computed by this function down there.
So, this is, in some sense, the wholemeal
approach, because we expressed the application
of "scene" to these elements in one go.
There is no loop counter, no explicit loop
control, or something like that.
So, it is the same reasons that I mentioned
there, why this is not the same as doing looping
in an imperative language.
In the same sense, this is wholemeal as opposed
to a piecemeal approach.
So, there wasn't any conceptual consideration
of one happens after another.
That is simply not happening here.
One could, of course, have performed this
computation somehow recursively, defining
a recursive function, but why should we do
this?
Why should we bother with this?
So, programming a recursion here would have
exposed some kind of traversal order which
we don't need, if we are simply interested
in "we have these pictures".
As I already mentioned, in the mathematical
set notation, we simply get: "for all numbers
in a certain range, ..." or maybe even "all
the numbers" if we have infinite lists, we
compute some value, and we get the result
of that.
That's it.
In one go rather than writing a loop counter
and a looping program.
Of course, the individual evaluation of these
Pictures (the computation of the different
scenes) will still happen in some order on
a sequential machine.
And also, the list is a sequence, it is not
a mathematical set.
So, it has some order.
But the individual values are independent
of order.
So, it doesn't matter whether I first compute
the third thing and then the zeroth thing,
or the other way around.
The values will be independent of that because
they are independent computations.
There is no effect that somehow goes and influences
the third computation based on what happened
in the first computation.
That is because these are values that are
computed from expressions.
Indeed, one can show some properties that
wouldn't hold in an incremental iterative
looping fashion.
So, somehow, expressing this idea that the
results do not depend on in which order we
compute them.
One way to capture this idea would be the
equivalence that is shown here.
What it is saying is:
If I take some numbers from zero to n, and
then compute "f of a" (f a) on each element,
and then put the results in a list, it is
the same as if I first reversed this number
list, so I get the numbers from n to zero,
still computing f on each of those values
and then reversing the list again.
Of course, I need this second "reverse" in
order to arrange the results in the correct
sequence.
But the point is that *when* I compute a certain
"f" of a certain "a" doesn't influence the
values that I get.
Because of that, these two lists will be the
same.
If I take the numbers in opposite order, I
get the same values.
I just get them in the opposite order, so
I have to reverse again at the end.
And something like that wouldn't be true for
a for-loop, for example.
We can actually check this be looking at some
C-like or Java-like code or Python-like code
or whatever.
So, let's take two for-loops which roughly
correspond to the two directions in which
one could compute such an iteration.
In the upper two lines, we have a for-loop
which also goes from zero to n, incrementing
this loop counter and then always computing
"f of a", and then storing this in a list,
or an array in this case.
And here we have the opposite case, where
we go from n to zero and count downwards and
also put the results in a list or in an array.
But in C or Java it is not true that we can
always replace this by this, for various reasons,
like side effects, like things that the f-calls
could be doing in addition to computing values.
So, these are not two pieces of code that
are always interchangeable in a language like
Java or C.
Of course, there is also this loop indexing
which in itself is against the spirit of wholemeal
programming.
You could say: But well, at least with Java
iterators one could work around this, and
then it wouldn't look like array indexing.
But even then, these two pieces of code, or
similar pieces of code, wouldn't be equivalent.
And even if you have special situations, where
the f is very well behaving (it is not doing
any prints or reads or whatever, it is not
changing variable values), even then this
is more difficult to handle than an equation.
We can turn the equation from the previous
slide to this more general version where the
"reverse" switches to the other side.
This makes these two expressions more symmetric.
And of course, this doesn't apply just to
numbered lists.
We can take arbitrary lists, and this property
will still be true for whatever f and list
we have, and actually for a whole class of
functions in place of this "reverse".
And it can directly be used for manipulating
programs by algebraic transformations in the
same way as we have seen on previous occasions
in the lecture already with different laws.
So, this is what Richard referred to in the
other quote as lawful program construction.
To think about laws that the functions in
our programs satisfy.
They could also be used for QuickCheck testing.
There we are also interested in properties.
And this could be a property that is of interest
in that context.
Also, this property is actually relevant for
the "isPalindrome" example again.
Probably, many of you have a solution to "isPalindrome"
(along with lower/upper case characters) which
somehow has something like "reverse" of a
list, where each element from a String has
been given to the toUpper- or toLower-function.
And then if you see something like that, you
can replace it by this.
And maybe this makes the overall computation
more efficient because then you can change
or save some of the computation.
Or maybe the other way around.
Maybe you have the second line in your code,
and when you move the "reverse" outside of
this list, you realize that you can share
this expression as a common subexpression
with some other piece of your function definition.
And then suddenly you have a more efficient
program, where you don't need to traverse
a list with toUpper or toLower two times.
So, that is a benefit of having laws like
this available.
And it comes from how we express our computations.
Just to drive home this point, let us consider
another example, which is somewhat artificial.
Let's assume we want to multiply each element
of an array or a list by its position in that
structure, and we want to sum up all the resulting
values.
That's an easy enough problem.
In whatever imperative language you know,
often you would solve it in a similar manner
as this one.
So, we need to have some declarations, but
these are not really the problem here.
Of course, we need to be sure about how we
start the result computation, how we initialize
this, etc.
But that is not the point here.
The point is that then we go through this
loop.
So, we need to make sure where we start, we
need to have an end condition, we need to
increment, and then we have our computation
that we do in each iteration of the loop.
And this looks about right.
This is a valid program for computing what
is written above.
But one could say, and should probably acknowledge,
that this suffers from the indexitis problem.
How does this manifest here?
For example, we need to know upfront how array
indices are counted in the language.
So, we could easily make an off-by-one error,
if we forget that we have to start counting
from zero.
We need to make sure that we increment instead
of decrement here.
We need to make sure that we have the right
end condition here, that we check that i is
smaller than n, and not, for example, that
i is equal to n, or smaller-equal to n, or
something like that.
So, in fact, there are at least three places
here where we could make an off-by-one error.
We could make a mistake here by starting from
the wrong start index.
We could make a mistake here by being off
by one, instead of comparing to n comparing
to n - 1 or n + 1, for example.
And even here, there is this issue that we
have to make sure that we have the right idea
of how arrays are counted.
So, is the first entry 0, or is the first
entry 1?
So, how do we make the correct index access
here?
That is because of this solution being based
on index accessing and looping, in this explicit
fashion.
In contrast, let us look at how the same problem
could be solved in Haskell.
So, of course in Haskell, we could also write
a recursive function which essentially does
the same kind of iteration as the for-loop
does in the previous slide.
But actually, I would propose this as a solution
to this problem in a more wholemeal fashion
or spirit.
I would argue that this is very nice, short
and declarative.
So, it exactly expresses what we want to do.
It takes this list.
It says that we want to basically combine
each list element with consecutive numbers.
We can express this by saying: let's pair
this by zipping with 0, 1, 2, ([0..]).
Then it takes all these pairs that it has
created and computes the multiplication, and
then this is summed up.
You can't really get it any shorter or more
declarative than this, in one go expressing
what's happening here.
Notice the difference in approach from the
previous solution.
There is no result variable that is somehow
overwritten again and again in a loop.
We don't need to have an explicit end condition.
There is no reference, even, to the length
of the list (n).
That is simply not needed here because the
zip will simply exhaust as many elements from
this infinite list as are needed in order
to have enough numbers.
So, there is no comparison against an end value,
like n or n - 1 or anything like that.
We also can't make any real errors this way.
This is just an expression which computes
something.
There is no looping with a loop condition,
no overwriting of result variable or anything
like that.
With this "zip" trick, it is also very interesting
that we don't need to know, in advance, how
many values we will need.
Because, simply, there will be as many consumed
from this infinite list as are needed for
our given finite list (assuming that this
list is finite).
You could, of course, argue that this is cheating
because I used the "sum" function here.
So, maybe this is only short because I used
the "sum" function instead of this repeated
accumulation of the addition.
But I would argue that this is really besides
the point.
On the one hand, it is a convenience function,
but even without having this available or
programmed by somebody else, it would have
been only a few keystrokes to express the
summation.
So, even if we don't have the "sum" function,
we can write this with maybe ten more keystrokes.
We can also express the summation with a higher-order
function (see later), and we would still get
this nice declarative expression.
And even if in the C, Python, or Java
version, you would somehow allow yourself
to use a convenient array sum function, that
wouldn't really have made the program from
the previous slide more declarative or nicer
to deal with.
So, if you actually sit down and try to think
about how you would program the for-loop based
version with a helper function for summing,
then you have to think:
What do I do with the array elements?
Where do I store them?
Do I overwrite my original array, so that
then I can call the sum-function on that array
(but then I have destroyed my input data)?
Or do I introduce a helper array in which
I first store all the multiplications and
then I use my sum-function on that helper
array, and then I have to discard it again?
Things like this appear in this piecewise
approach with looping, whereas here we simply
have one expression which says all there is
to say about this problem.
So, if the presence or absence of the sum function
is not what really differentiates the two
cases, the Haskell version and imperative
version, then let's discuss what are the actual
issues here.
It's mainly about expressiveness and susceptibility
to change and refactoring, so how easy it
is to maintain or change this code.
Let's say we decided that actually the counting
of positions should start at 1 instead of
0.
We have the same computation again, but now
we actually want the first element to be multiplied
by 1.
This could certainly be done both for the
imperative and for the Haskell version.
Let's look at the C-like version.
There we had this loop before, and now we
could actually make this change by saying:
Well, we will actually start at 1 with our
index variable.
That also means we have to make sure that
we don't count to below n, but actually up
to n.
Otherwise, we would stop one step too early.
And we have to make sure that when we access
our arrays, since their numbering scheme hasn't
changed (simply because I want to compute
the first multiplication with 1 instead of
0, doesn't mean that somehow C has decided
that it will change how arrays are accessed),
while I multiply with 1, I still need to access
the array element at position 0.
So, actually, in order to make this change,
I had to change 3 places in this code.
It could be done in a different way, but even
then, there is this potential for error.
There are several places where I can make
an error.
I have to decide where do I start?
Where do I stop?
How do I access the data structure elements?
So, there are several places where I can make
an off-by-one error.
And everything has to fit together in order
to really express what I wanted to change
about my computation here.
In contrast, in the Haskell version, if I
want to make this change, I want to multiply
the first element by 1 instead of 0, then
what do I change?
I change one 0 into one 1.
That's all I need to do in order to express
this desired change.
I don't have to think about the loop end condition,
because there is no loop end condition.
And then I talked about n or n - 1 or n +
1.
I don't have to talk about this here either.
I only make the change which is relevant.
I also don't have to think about how my list
is indexed (how do I access the zeroth, or
first or second element?) because there is
no indexing.
Since I don't access elements of this list
by index, I don't have to change anything
about this.
In that sense, this is the minimal change,
and the desired change.
There shouldn't be more need for changes.
In that sense, one could say this is a more
maintainable program because we can make
desired changes in one local place.
Of course, I don't want to be lying; one could
argue that on the C version one could also
have made the change by a smaller edit.
One could say: Even in the C version, I didn't
need to do what I did on the previous slide.
I could instead have changed the multiplication
down here.
So, leaving the array start and end as they
were, and simply somehow changing this multiplier
here.
And accidentally, that would actually also
have led to the same behaviour.
But I would argue, it's just indexitis in
a different form.
So, I still have to find the place where to
make this change.
It's somehow strange, that now I have to think
that I multiply the (i+1)-th thing with the
array at index i.
I have to make sure that I don't make an off-by-one
error here.
I avoided changing the loop iteration header
here, but it is not really nice that I have
these strange differences in what do I multiply
with which array element.
So, I might consider this as a better change
rather than the one on the previous slide.
But even just the fact that there *are* these
two separate changes which lead to the desired
behaviour, could also be seen as ground for
worry.
I want to change where I start my multiplying.
In the Haskell version, there is exactly one
place where I make this change, and it expresses
everything there is to express.
In the C version, there are several ways of
doing this, and each of these ways has the
potential for making errors by changing not
all of the 3 places, or only the wrong place
where a change could be made.
So, that certainly takes more thinking by
the programmer rather than having this very
declarative way where we have exactly one
place that makes a difference between these
two versions of the program.
So, why is it that the C version has to make
all these clerical decisions?
Decisions that are not really significant
from an algorithmic perspective, but are simply
there because you have to make sure that you
get everything right about the loop start,
the loop end, and array indexing, etc.
Why is that?
Well, conceptually, it is because the C version
doesn't have a separation of the values that
you want to enumerate and process, on the
one hand, and loop control on the other hand.
It is all one big mess.
In this example, it is not yet a *big* mess,
but things that have to be kept synchronized.
In larger examples, it really can become a
big mess to deal with all of these aspects
at once because there is no separation of
these concerns.
In contrast, in the Haskell version, we have
this perfect separation.
It actually comes, in this specific example,
from this expression.
We express that we want to combine the things
from whatever list comes here with values
starting from k and however far along we have
to go until we have processed all the values.
This is somehow where the loop control, if
you want, is situated.
But there *is* no explicit loop control.
You simply express what should be computed.
So, basically, this Haskell version does not
need explicit loop control.
It does not access data structure elements
by index.
That is again the point that I have made several
times now, that in Haskell, you should, and
can almost always, avoid the use of indexing
operators.
Because that's not how you think about data
structures in Haskell (by piecewise access
to individual elements).
You think about data structures as a whole,
and the operation that happens on the data
structure as a whole.
So, we don't need to increment the loop counter.
We don't need to talk about the loop end condition
in the Haskell version, simply because of
this expressiveness, that particularly in
this case, infinite lists do have.
That is the point, that we can use an infinite
list basically as a structuring tool here,
and still, what will be computed is exactly
only as many elements from this list as are
needed.
So, this is somehow a concern that the evaluation
mechanism of the language performs for us.
We don't have to think about this as a programmer.
That is what is helping us here and avoids
all these clerical decisions that the C version
has to make:
Where do I start counting?
How to increment?
Where do I end counting?
Am I sure that I have done exactly as many
iterations as I need?
Or one too many?
One too few?
How do I access elements by index?
All these things disappear if we express the
solution in this more declarative way.
Now, you could think this all is just propaganda.
At least, you could be suspicious.
Maybe I am fooling myself about efficiency.
So, certainly, you could think, the C code
is more efficient than my declarative code.
It seems like a reasonable thing to assume, that
for example, here, we probably compute this
extra list.
So, this needs extra memory, and then we traverse
data several times.
Even when I discussed the C version with this
helper function "sum", I mentioned that we
would probably want to either overwrite our
first array, or create a helper array.
So, certainly in the Haskell version, we also
have these aspects.
So, certainly, this is less efficient.
So, we shouldn't go for this declarative version,
however nice I am trying to sell it to you.
Because this program is simply more efficient,
because it does a very tight loop and does
exactly what is needed to do.
Maybe it is not nicely expressed because
I can make errors in all these places, but
at least it does it in an efficient way.
So, that could be your counterargument to
even trying to write a program like this,
where everything is more maintainable because
we have a clearer separation of concerns.
That could be a concern that you have at this
point.
Well, actually no.
That might seem like a valid concern, but
it doesn't really apply.
We do have compilers.
And compilers can translate declarative code
as you have just seen into a tight C-like
loop without using intermediate data structures,
just fine.
So, this is not really an issue.
Of course, the program might ultimately still
be less efficient than a handwritten C program,
but it's not on an order of magnitudes.
For example, the compiler can even spot parallelization
opportunities.
Thanks to the independent values aspect that
we discussed when comparing list comprehensions
against for-loops, it is easier (in a program
as we have just seen) to spot places where
parallelization could happen; much simpler
than, for example, in a C program.
This also all has to do with the lawful program
construction aspect of the quote by Richard.
So, the fact that we have laws about our programs
can also be exploited by a compiler.
The compiler can apply laws to eliminate inefficiencies,
data structures traversals, data structures
themselves.
This is actually what GHC is doing.
So, GHC isn't actually on its own introducing
parallelism, but it pays a lot of attention
to, for example, traversal of data structures,
and can eliminate many of them.
So, as a programmer, we can actually afford
to write nice declarative expressions because
we rely on the compiler to optimize our programs.
And the compiler can perform a lot of optimizations,
because of the laws that apply to our programs,
and because of the purity.
So, everything is pure by default, unlike
in C, where we would need extra annotations
and even then, the compiler cannot make as
many changes to the code as it might want
from a, so to speak, more algorithmic perspective.
So, in a functional language, much more transformation
of programs is possible in an automatic fashion,
because there is more semantic knowledge about
the programs than in an imperative language.
We could also talk more about refactoring.
I don't want to do this at this point.
This was an excurse into this subject of wholemeal
programming.
So, I don't want to spend too much time of
this week's lecture time on it.
Also, of course, you could argue or wonder
why I made this artificial example.
For presentation's sake, of course.
So, is this really representative of real
situations?
My wholehearted claim is: Yes!
I cannot prove this to you in this lecture.
But that's the experience that comes from
programming in a declarative fashion.
So, this is really representative.
It is not just something that happened in
this small example.
These differences are real.
And they are relevant.